<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="true"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>257</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">zzhaoe-002D</fr:addr><fr:route>zzhaoe-002D.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="The illusory middle landscape">The illusory middle landscape</fr:title><fr:taxon>Musings</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2025</fr:year><fr:month>1</fr:month><fr:day>10</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="ericczhao.xml"
addr="ericczhao"
title="Eric Zhao">Eric Zhao</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Plenty of people have spoken or written about the enduring mystic of <fr:link
type="local"
href="the-elder-scrolls-v-skyrim.xml"
addr="the-elder-scrolls-v-skyrim"
title="The Elder Scrolls V: Skyrim"><fr:em>Skyrim</fr:em></fr:link>.<html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
class="sidenote-number"><html:span
class="sidenote">So I shall, shamelessly, add my own. In fact, I wrote one several years ago for a course blog. Although it had a similar kind of focus, it possessed a rather different flavor.</html:span></html:span>
 In spite of newer experiences which may boast gripping narratives or real-to-life visuals or delightful gameplay loops, those whose hearts upon which has lain the tender yet unyielding hold of idyllic Tamriel find themselves returning again and again, even nigh fifteen years now, to that northern corner of the world. By most reasonable measures the game's combat mechanics are rather lacking; the quest writing varies from uninspired to abominable; the whole experience is rife with visual and functional deficiency and defect, of both comic and exasperating character. Yet somehow it is a spring from which all weariness seems to depart; when novelties have worn off, one remembers the rugged peak and the rolling pastures, the surly wanderer and the unassuming stableboy, the hidden cove and the homely home.</fr:p><fr:p>At some point, I discovered mods, and then the possibilities had truly opened before me. For by way of the bottomless trove of fan-made modifications I could make the world a place of my own: new characters to befriend, equipment to craft; fair vistas to behold, deep dungeons to crawl. In short time I discovered, somewhat paradoxically, that I could only best feed my wants and my wonders by imposing restrictions. It is absurd, after all, to wade an icy bay or eat a half-quiver of arrows without much thought; one should suffer, respectively, hypothermia and outright death. One should wonder why prisoners remain in their chains and carriage drivers at their seats if instantaneous teleportation to any point-of-interest costs neither money nor effort. Until then I had cared for good cooking only after a brutal stabbing. Now I respected the snow squalls and esteemed the bow; I cherished my feet and my mare; I welcomed to my parched lips even the most insipid soup and stale loaf after any brief jaunt in the woods. For the harsh land of the Nords demands hardy living; by endurance one claims the high ridge; through peril comes the richest spoil; it is hinter that makes home. The untamed grasses rush furiously, I can see the glowing parapet, nigh is the slumbering grove; here I stand. Its name is Wilderness—yet not altogether Wild.</fr:p><fr:p>This was the reality away from reality: the middle landscape, fraught with many dangers—but comforts are never so out of reach. I sought more, driven to wilder wilds, homelier homes. But satisfaction is a doomed pursuit, a chasing after the wind. There is always some greater adventure to be tasted. It is this regrettable truth that, whilst no longer surprising, never loses its vexing flavour. For the sub-creation of man, though it may refract and magnify the splintered rays of the primary creation, remains just that: a partial mosaic of the hale light. And man whose heart was made for the light has fallen very far into the shadows.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="References">References</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>259</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">the-elder-scrolls-v-skyrim</fr:addr><fr:route>the-elder-scrolls-v-skyrim.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="The Elder Scrolls V: Skyrim">The Elder Scrolls V: Skyrim</fr:title><fr:taxon>Reference</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2011</fr:year></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="bethesdagamestudios.xml"
addr="bethesdagamestudios"
title="Bethesda Game Studios">Bethesda Game Studios</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter /><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree><fr:tree
toc="false"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="false"
expanded="true"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:title
text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title><fr:authors /></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:tree
toc="true"
numbered="false"
show-heading="true"
show-metadata="true"
expanded="false"
root="false"
xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml"><fr:frontmatter><fr:anchor>261</fr:anchor><fr:addr
type="user">zzhaoe-002E</fr:addr><fr:route>zzhaoe-002E.xml</fr:route><fr:title
text="Poorly modernising &quot;The Battle of Brunanburh&quot;">Poorly modernising "The Battle of Brunanburh"</fr:title><fr:taxon>Musings</fr:taxon><fr:date><fr:year>2024</fr:year><fr:month>10</fr:month><fr:day>20</fr:day></fr:date><fr:authors><fr:author><fr:link
type="local"
href="ericczhao.xml"
addr="ericczhao"
title="Eric Zhao">Eric Zhao</fr:link></fr:author></fr:authors></fr:frontmatter><fr:mainmatter><fr:p>Since ceasing to <fr:link
type="local"
href="zzhaoe-002D.xml"
addr="zzhaoe-002D"
title="The illusory middle landscape">return again and again to Skyrim</fr:link>, I have found that I return again and again to a desire to study Anglo-Saxon, for which I had taken a class a couple of years ago as a sophomore at <fr:link
type="local"
href="umich.xml"
addr="umich"
title="The University of Michigan">Michigan</fr:link>. There were five or six of us enrolled,<html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
class="sidenote-number"><html:span
class="sidenote">Mostly, from what I recall, seniors in the German department; though this is probably really inaccurate. But the best student seemed to be a Middle-Eastern studies fellow.</html:span></html:span>
 though on a typical day only three or four might show up to class, which centered mostly around reading and modernising texts in Moore and Knott's <fr:link
type="local"
href="moore-knott-the-elements-of-old-english.xml"
addr="moore-knott-the-elements-of-old-english"
title="The Elements of Old English, 10th ed."><fr:em>The Elements of Old English</fr:em></fr:link>, 10th ed. There was some discussion of sound changes which I've entirely forgotten. It was sometimes a slog, sometimes great fun, and anyways it has been difficult to keep up since then, however much I would like. In recent weeks I've been slowly working through <fr:em><fr:link
type="local"
href="evans-an-introduction-to-old-english.xml"
addr="evans-an-introduction-to-old-english"
title="An Introduction to Old English">An Introduction to Old English</fr:link></fr:em>.<html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
class="sidenote-number"><html:span
class="sidenote">The power of the interlibrary loan is not to be understated.</html:span></html:span>
 It's proven to be, in many ways, substantially more digestible.</fr:p><fr:p>I could complain much about the textbooks and the other resources, but probably, at the end of the day, I just don't practice it enough. So here's to more practice,<html:span
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
class="sidenote-number"><html:span
class="sidenote">And to work these sidenotes to the limit.</html:span></html:span>
 by glossing and modernising the famous "The Battle of Brunanburh", the only poem I've worked through in its entirety in the past. The text is the <fr:link
type="external"
href="https://oepoetryfacsimile.org/?document=8412">edition</fr:link> in the <fr:link
type="local"
href="foys-oepf3.xml"
addr="foys-oepf3"
title="Old English Poetry in Facsimile 3.0">OEPF</fr:link>, edited by <fr:link
type="local"
href="martinfoys.xml"
addr="martinfoys"
title="Martin Foys">Martin Foys</fr:link>.</fr:p></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:mainmatter><fr:backmatter /></fr:tree></fr:backmatter></fr:tree>